你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到pwn学院的竞争条件模块
welcome back to the race conditions module of pwn College
我是Yan，在这个视频中我们将要谈论
I'm Yan and in this video we'll be talking about
文件系统中的竞争
races in the file system
这是竞态条件的特例
right this is a kind of special case of race conditions
或者利用特定竞争条件的策略
or the strategy of exploiting particular race conditions
如果你还记得
if you recall
攻击者利用竞争条件的方法是
an attacker exploits a race condition by changing
修改程序期望的运行状态
the state that a program expects to be functioning in
即在程序使用和修改此状态之间的运行状态
between the time the program makes use of this state and the time it modifies this state
好的
right
程序对状态的了解
so some assumption made by the program about the state
不准确了
ceases to be true
因为攻击者改变了它
because the attacker changed it
要想利用竞争条件
right and so to exploit the race condition
如果程序有不安全假设
if there's a kind of unsafe assumption made by the program
攻击者需要能够影响环境或程序状态
the attacker needs to be able to impact the environment or the the state of a program
一个常见的例子就是文件系统
a common case of this is the file system
文件系统是共享资源
now of course a file system is a shared resource
通常
and oftentimes as an attacker
攻击者可以访问部分文件系统
you would have access to parts of the file system
且漏洞程序默认它不会被篡改
that the victim program assumes aren't being maliciously modified
让我们来看一看
let's take a look
这是一个示例程序
all right here's an example program
这个程序创建了一个shell脚本
this program writes a
它会输出 safe 字符串
script that basically just echoes safe
然后程序执行了这个脚本
and then it execl that script
一个非常简单的小程序
a very small simple program
但这个程序存在严重漏洞
but this program is extremely vulnerable
因为在创建脚本
because in between this when the file is created
和 sh 执行脚本之间
and after /bin/sh starts up and begins to execute it
任何事情都可能发生在这个文件上
anything could happen to that file for example
它可能被攻击者替换掉
it might be replaced by any attacker that has access to do so alright
实际利用一下，来看看效果
let's take a look at how this might work by exploiting it actually
清空一下窗口
let's clear out all of these windows
好的，太棒了
okay awesome so
拷贝源代码到这个文件中
I copy that source code into this file here basically
非常简单的程序
very simple program again
它只是
all it does opens the
打开在命令行指定的文件
file that we give on the command line
写入shell脚本，然后执行
writes a shell script to it and executes it
启动它
if we run it
并指定一个asdf的文件
and give it an ASDF file
它会打印出safe
it'll print out safe alright
我们如何利用这个呢
so how do we exploit this
很明显
well obviously
说很明显，有点夸张
I mean obviously bit of
在创建和执行脚本之间替换脚本
exploit this by replacing this file between the time it's created and the time it's executed
程序假定了这个文件此时不会被修改
the program of course is written to assume that this file does not change
但是是可以的
but this file can change
我们看一下
let's take a look
好的
alright so
我在其它窗口执行了这个命令
I must be running the command somewhere in a different window
等一下，我找一下给它关了
one second let me find it and stop it
真是，抱歉了
yep I am sorry about that
好的
alright
运行程序
so we run the program
它创建了asdf文件
it creates this asdf file
内容包含指定/bin/sh，和输出safe
says that  /bin/sh and then echo safe
当执行它时
and then when it executes it of course
会打印出safe
it prints out safe and that's what it does all right
嗯
um
那么如果
so what happens if
我们频繁的用输出flag的脚本替换asdf
we just try as often as possible to replace that file with a file that cats our flag
这儿有一个catflag脚本
so we have this cat flag script
好的，内容是cat /flag
alright cat /flag
我们要做的是
and what we're going to do is
写一个程序…while循环……它会循环…不好意思
write a program that ... while ... that'll just loop ... sorry the
简单写一个shell命令，在死循环中
write a quick shell command that'll loop in an infinite loop and
持续的用catflag覆盖asdf文件
continuously copy catflag over this asdf file
我们使用cp的-v
and we're going to dash v
然后boom，成功了
and then boom here it is
持续覆盖asdf文件
just copying continuously over asdf file
就是个循环，你也可以用Python实现
just a simple loop you could write this of course in Python
你可以用C写，用什么写都行
you can write it in C you can write in anything
我用bash写的
I wrote it in bash
好的，接着我们运行这个
all right and then we're gonna run this
这次竞争失败了
and of course that time we lost the race
它创建了ASDF文件
right it created ASDF file
先执行了，然后asdf才被覆盖
and it executed before our other script was able to overwrite it
这次又失败了
that time you lost the race again
这次竞争成功了
that time you won the race
好的
all right
很有趣，对吧
pretty interesting right because
如果单看程序的实现
if you just look at how this program works
它看起来还是挺安全的
it doesn't look like it should be unsafe
但因为在你电脑里同时有很多进程在执行
but because there are multiple things going on on your computer at the same time
它默认了共享资源是安全的
because this is making security critical assumptions on a shared resource
而这个共享资源并不能确保不被修改
that is not immune from tampering
问题就来了
problems happen
好的
all right
让我们
let's
当然
of course
这个例子很好
this case was extremely nice
修改的机会窗口很大
in the sense that there was a huge window of opportunity
文件打开后（到执行它前）有很长一段时间
a very long time between the time when this file is opened
顺便说一下，文件打开后会有一个文件描述符
by the way once the file is opened and there's a file descriptor
然后就不用管磁盘上的文件了
then we can move this file out of the way
覆盖它也没问题
just fine to overwrite it
这里的write只会修改内存里的
this write goes to the opened resource
它和磁盘中的文件已经没有关系了
it has nothing to do with the file name anymore
如果我们在打开和写入之间覆盖了磁盘上的文件
so if we overwrite the file between this open and this write
我们还是赢。这个写入不会覆盖我们的新文件
we still win. the write won't overwrite our new file
基本上只要我们的重写发生在
and basically as long as we overwrite
程序open文件之后
this file between the time and it's open
在sh完成初始化前
and between the time and after /bin/sh initializes itself
这要很长时间，会调用许多系统调用
which takes a long time many system calls etc
Linux二进制文件加载的那一套
all of that Linux binary loading
然后才会去打开shell脚本
and it finally opens the shell script that it wrote
我们有充足的时间替换shell脚本
we have all of that time to replace that shell script with our attack
好的，加点难度
alright so let's tighten up that race
让它更难竞争成功
what if you make it less winnable
这是一个更难竞争的程序
this is a much less raceable program
基本上
where basically we have a
我们复制了echo程序，然后输出 SAFE
we copy in Echo and we just run Echo Safe
我们打开/bin/echo
right so we open bin Echo
打开提供给我们的文件
we open the file that's provided we
复制echo程序到新文件中
copy using sent file bin Echo to our new file
关闭新文件，然后执行它
we close the file and then we execute
（机会）小多了
alright much smaller
没有/bin/sh了
no /bin/sh
在echo被打开的那一刻（代码06行）
the moment that Echo is opened here
游戏结束了
it's game over
如果错过了窗口
right if we've lost our windows
窗口在这个open和这个execl调用之间
our windows again between this open and then this execl call
调用execl的那一刻
the moment execl is called
如果还没替换，就竞争失败了
we have now lost the race if we haven't replaced it between here
显然这个窗口要小得多，没有sh初始化的过程了
obviously this window is much smaller there's no sh initialization
所以要赢就更难了
so it'll be much tougher to win
让我展示给你看
let me show you
更难竞争成功了
first of all that it is tougher to win
我们要
we're going to
回顾一下fs1
I recall our fs1 example right
我们经常获胜
that we can win fairly frequently
让我们
let's actually
运行2000次
let's run it 2,000 times
看看获胜的频率
and see how frequently we win
好的，开始
okay here we go
把结果写入output文件
I'm going to write this to a file called output
然后用命令
then I'm going to use some commands to
计算出成功概率为50%
figure out that we win about half of the time
所以我们运行了2000次
so we ran a 2000 times
另一个窗口发起的攻击
about half of the time our attack running in this other window
半数都竞争成功了
won the game force over half the time
显然会有一些噪音
that time obviously there's some noise
取决于我的系统还在做什么等等
depending on what else my system is doing and so forth
这就是原来的这个
so that was this the original this
在第一个例子中，我们有一半的胜算
this first example we won half the time
让我们来看第二个例子
let's see the second example
用这个攻击方式能赢多少次
how often we win that with just this simple attack
很明显
obviously
这里是例子2的实现
this is the I implemented that example as well here
预计攻击成功率不高
and we expect to see a less successful attack
让我们试一试
let's give that a try
不用fs1，改用fs2
instead of FS1 let's do FS2
你马上就能看到
and so right away you can see
带有pwn_college的flag少了很多
there's a lot less say pwn college a lot less flags leaked
具体来说，我们在2000次中只赢了45次
and specifically we won out of 2000 times only 45 times
好的，我们再试一次
right let's try that again
只有48次
only 48 times
还挺稳定的
that's fairly stable right
竞争成功的次数少了很多很多
we win much much much fewer of those races
那么我们怎样才能做得更好呢
so how can we do better
总的思路是让程序慢下来
well the general idea is to slow things down
具体说就是让目标程序变慢
and specifically slow down the victim program
这个漏洞程序
this vulnerable program
如果你让它跑得慢一点
if you make it run slower
如果你让他俩之间的间隔变长
if you make it take longer between this and this
那么你将扩大机会窗口
then you'll open that vulnerable window more
我们来看几个选项
so let's see a couple of options
一个是降低该进程的调度优先级
one option is reducing the scheduling priority of this process
有几种方法可以做到这一点
there are several ways to do this
Linux提供了一个工具和一个叫做 utility 的系统
Linux provides a utility and a system called utility of course
使用一个叫 nice 的系统调用
uses this system call called nice
思路是被标记为nice的程序对资源的要求不高
the idea is a program that is nice takes up is less demanding of your resources
它更偏好不被调度
so it is much more willing to be unscheduled
这是在告诉内核，嘿
it's kind of telling the kernel hey
让我运行在后台就行
run me in the background
如果需要执行其他命令
if you need to execute other commands
就先暂停我吧，执行其他命令
pause my process and execute
我们只有有限的资源
of course we have finite amount of course
许多进程都在争夺注意力
many processes vying for attention
如果你把程序标记为nice
if you put a program nice
它就不太可能一次执行完
it will be much less likely to run all the way through
它更有可能被暂停
it'll be much more likely to pause
来给其他程序运行的机会
to be paused to give other programs a chance to run
如果它停在我们的机会窗口
if it's paused right here during our vulnerable window
那么我们就能竞争成功
then we can win that race right
你使用的方式很好
the way you use nice
您只需在要运行的命令前面加上nice
you just put nice in front of the command you want to run
它会被降低调度优先级
and it will get descheduled
还有ionice。都是一样的
there's also ionice. it's the same
nice对应CPU
nice is for CPU
ionice对应磁盘的输入输出
ionice is for input outputs for your disk
因此，它将大大减少对磁盘的使用
so it'll be much less intensive on your disk usage
让我们看一下这对竞争成功率的影响
so let's take a look at what this does to our success
我们做2000次
so here we do 2000 times
但这次我们把nice放在前面
but now we will put nice in front of this
还是在后台攻击
we still have the attack running in the background
持续用catflag替换asdf
copying cat flag over ASDF
我们运行一下
let's run this
好像没啥用
and that did not help
这确实要看情况
it really depends
这取决于你的机器在做什么
really depends on what your machine is doing
我不确定是否有统计上显著的系数
I would not sure if there's a statistically significant factor
nice 接受一个优先级参数，从-20
nice takes a priority between negative 20
这是非常非常高的优先级
which is very very high priority
我知道这很令人困惑。它是一个负数
I know it's confusing. it's a negative number
但它表示一直调度我
but it is schedule me at all times
我需要一直运行
I absolutely need to run
还有19
and 19
默认情况下，如果直接用nice，优先级是10
and by default if you just do nice it'll put 10
19 则告诉你别安排我
19 tells you you know just don't schedule me
除非计算机没别的要执行了
only schedule me if you know the computer isn't doing anything else etc
效果并不显著
and it's not having a significant effect
看起来我们赢了33次
looks like we win 33
是的，效果不是很好。我们看看ionice
yeah these aren't. let's see about ionice
ionice有一个类别参数
ionice has a class
类别1、2和3
class 1 2 and 3
3基本上表示只在空闲时使用IO
3 basically just says use io only when we are idle
我们来看看
let's see if that
这似乎没有帮助
it didn't seem to have helped
确实没帮助
it did not help
好吧
well
取决于电脑还在做什么
depending on what else the computer is doing
所以让我们
so let's actually
启动一些
let's spin up a bunch of
nope I'll spin up a bunch of
C语言中的循环
loops in C
好了，现在他们用了更多的CPU
all right now they're using more CPU
也许nice会
so maybe nice will actually
会有用，不像在一个完全（没事做的机器中）
have some effect unlike on a completely
不是吧
really
让我们耗光CPU
okay let's use up all of my CPU
希望它还能对正在录制的视频进行编码
hopefully it'll still encode this video that I'm recording
好的
all right
演示失败
failed demo
没关系
that's okay
有时这个可行，有时不可行
sometimes this works sometimes this does not work
这取决于
it really depends on
竞争类型
what type of race it is
窗口中发生了什么
what is going on in that window
如果程序是CPU占用高的，nice会更有帮助
if it was CPU heavy nice would be much more helpful
等等
and so on alright
录制视频之前的练习中，效果很好
in my practice before the recording it worked great
嗯
um
把这些都关掉
let's kill all of this
确保这是
make sure that that is
嗯
um
没关掉
that did not
好了
alright there we go
我把这些循环都关了
I killed all of those our loops alright
不幸的是
unfortunately
nice没展示成功
no nice first
我们看看nice是否对第一个例子有用
let's see if actually nice should do nicely for our first one
在没nice的情况下，成功了半数
so again we win about half of the races of the first one without nice
这个实际上调用了/bin/sh等等
um this one that that actually calls /bin/sh and so forth
加上nice试试
and with nice
表现更糟了
even worse all right
我们nice就到这里了
we're gonna move on from nice
还要讨论其他话题
because we need to cover other topics all right
好吧，nice没成功
all right nice didn't work out
你得相信刚刚讲的
you have to take my word for it
有时确实有用
it does sometimes
另一个概念是
another concept is
为了能减慢程序的速度
in terms of being able to slow down the program
如果程序允许你指定文件目录
if a program allows you to specify a path
可以通过指定很深很深的目录来减慢速度
you can slow down by having a lot of directories in that path
为什么这会让程序变慢
why does this slow things down
它能减慢速度
it slows things down
是因为当你要检查一大堆目录的时候
because when you have to look into a bunch of directories
当你指定/blah/blah/blah...
when you specify something like  slash blah slash blah
Linux内核必须进入每个目录
the Linux kernel has to go into each directory
查看该目录中的条目
look at the entries in that directory
确定下一个
identify the next one
进入目录
go into that
从磁盘获取数据，等等
fetch that from disk etc
这需要时间，对吧
it takes time right
所以你可以构造这些超长的路径
so you can build these super super long paths
减慢文件访问速度
to slow down that file access
当execl运行时
so that when this happens when execl runs
它要花很长时间来找到文件
it'll actually take a long time to find that file
给你更多的时间来替换它
giving you more time to replace it
酷
cool
不幸的是，Linux内核有一个
unfortunately the Linux kernel has a
路径大小限制为4,096字节，4kb
path sized limit of 4,096 bytes right 4 kilobytes
但这仍然是一条很长的路径
so that's still a very very long path
对于大多数目的，都足够了
probably sufficient for most purposes
但我们可以更进一步
but we can do even better
我们可以构建一个疯狂的文件系统迷宫
we can build this insane thing called a file system maze right
基本是有一个迷宫目录
we basically have a directory where the maze is
然后在里面创建目录
and then we create directories
相互嵌套的一组目录
a set of directories that are nested in each other
a/1/2/3/4/5等等
a slash 1 slash 2 slash 3 slash 4 slash 5 etc
最终用root符号链接绕回迷宫的起始位置
culminating in a symlink back to the root
b也是一样，b/1/2/等等等等
and same with b blah blah blah blah
最终用root符号链接回到起始位置
culminating the symlink back to the root
我们可以使用其它符号链接
and this allows us to using other symlinks
走到迷宫每条岔路的尽头，比如a的18
that go to the end of each individual maze entry here
我们可以创建这样一条路径
we can create a path that goes
/my/maze/a_end/root/b_end/root/c_end
my maze a_end root b_end root c_end
当这条路径被解析时
when this path is resolved what will actually happen
它会先到/my/maze
it'll go through my maze
然后会到a_end
and then it'll follow a_end
经过a/1/2/3/4/
then go a slash 1 slash 2 slash 3 slash 4 slash
因为a_end只是存储了实际路径的文本
because a_end just stores basically the text of the of the actual path
内核实际上会一次进入这些目录
and the kernel will actually have to follow all of these
深入到最后
dig in
然后通过root返回到入口
then follow root all the way back
然后进入b_end
and then it goes to B end
然后它要再经历一遍
and then it has to go through all of this again
然后经过root
then it goes through root
这一切都需要花费大量的时间
and this all takes enormous amounts of time
我们能做的就这么多了
there's only so much we can do here
Linux对每次路径解析有40个符号链接的限制
Linux has a limit of 40 symbolic links per path resolution
但每个符号链接的路径可达到4000字节
but each of these steps can be 4000 long right
所以你可以强迫内核遍历海量的目录
so that's an enormous amount of directories that you can force the kernel to traverse
看一下如何提高竞争成功率
let's take a look at how this impacts our success race
提醒一下
so as a reminder
别被nice困扰
let's not bother with nice
来吧
come on
好的
okay
尝试2000次这个更困难的攻击
so out of 2000 iterations on this tighter attack
用最初的攻击方法
with just this attack running
2000次我们成功了50次
we succeed about 50 times out of 2000 right
我们看一下迷宫的效果
let's look at maze
我建造了这个迷宫
I built this maze
这是a b a_end b_end c_end，等等
right so here is my a b a_end b_end c_end etc
一直到z
actually it did all through Z
a里面是1 2 3，以此类推，直到100
in a I have a 1 2 3 and so on all the way up until a 100
然后是root符号链接
and then I have the root symlink
回到maze目录
that goes back to my maze
就是这个
here it is
然后如果我对它解引用
and then if I dereference that
我能进到b
I can go into B
当然，这样很快就填满了路径的最大尺寸
right and of course I very quickly fill up the maximum size of a path
但我也可以用a_end
but I can also again do a_end
它一直到达a的末端
and that goes all the way to the end of a
里面有一个root
and there's a root thing there
我可以写a_end/root/b_end/root/c_end/root/d_end/root/e_end/root
so I can do a_end root b_end slash root c_end slash root d_end slash root e_end slash root
f_end/root/g_end/root/
f_end slash root g_end slash root and slash root
等下
wait
我复制写好的
I'm just gonna copy my other one
全打出来太费劲了
because to discombobulate it to type out all of it
等一下
one second
好了
here we go
让我们走出迷宫吧
let's get out of the maze
提出我要执行的
bring up what I was executing
在这里也可以做同样的事情
and in this exact same thing can be done here so
我走进了迷宫
I go into the maze
到了a_end
I go to a_end
回到迷宫起始位置
back out to the root of the maze
到b_end，返回到开始，到c_end，以此类推
b_end back out to the root c_end and so on
一直到s_end回到开始，再到t_end
I go here up until s_end back to the root t_end
基本上有40个符号链接了
I think this basically makes it 40 symbolic links
路径解析有40个符号链接的上限
again there's a limit of 40
你可以让每条分支走的更深
you can make it deeper
每条分支我只走到100
each entry in the root I only move and up to 100
但显然没满4000字节
but that's not 4,000 bytes obviously
我可以再深入一点，但这已经足够了
so I could probably go deeper but this is sufficient
遍历这个迷宫，然后一路回来
traversing this maze and then all the way back out
然后读取我一直在覆盖的asdf文件
and then reading that ASDF file that I've been overwriting
要花大量时间
is going to take time
之前2000次我们成功了50次
so again before we succeeded 50 times out of 2000
看看现在如何
let's see what happens now
能看到更多flag
you can see quite a lot more flags flying
好了，我们把成功率提高了五倍
boom we opt our success rate by a factor of five
当然，我们还可以把这个迷宫弄得更深
and we can of course make that maze even deeper
让程序的速度更慢
to slow down the program more to
让成功率更高
get things even more reliable
结论是
the takeaway is
如果想更高效赢得竞争
if you want to win races more effectively
你得想办法让程序慢下来
you need to find ways to slow down the program
文件系统竞争非常非常重要
file system races are super super relevant
事实上，这些问题直到今天还在发生
in fact these bugs occur to this day
这不是之前讲历史时的古老bug
these aren't archaic bugs that we're talking about historically
去年有一个ToC-ToU漏洞
last year there was a time of check time of use vulnerability
在Ubuntu的程序崩溃报告系统中被发现
found in Ubuntu's crash reporting system for program crashes
就是那个弹出窗口告诉你程序崩溃了的程序
and you get a pop up saying hey this crashed
如果你用的是Ubuntu
if you're using Ubuntu
在那里有一个toc-tou漏洞
there was a time of check time of use vulnerability in that
在这段Python代码中
in the Python code
另外这些漏洞
another thing is that these vulnerabilities
竞争条件不是C特有的
and race conditions in general are not just C specific
我们之前谈的很多
a lot of what we talk about
比如溢出等等
overflows and so forth
它们可能不适用于rust
they might not apply to for example rust
但这个适用范围很广
this does very much
这段Python代码检查用户是否
right so this Python code checked if the user
能否访问崩溃的文件路径
could access the file path that crashed
如果他们无法访问它
and if they could not access it
如果他们不能访问的话
if they could not access it
它会为崩溃事件创建一个新的报告文件
it creates a new report file for the crash
如果他们能访问的话
if they can access it
它就进入目录，解析它
then it goes in here and just parses it
直接解析它，默认用户具有相应权限
happily parse it assuming that the user has permissions
显然，这俩发生在不同的时间
of course this is not at a different time than this
它们中间有一个攻击窗口
and there's an attack window in between
利用方法为
so the exploit of course
先确保这个路径是可以访问的
is to make sure that the path is accessible
触发else条件
to trigger the else condition
然后迅速
then quickly
用符号链接将它指向你想读取的文件
symbolically link whatever that was pointing to something else that you want to read
使用它，你可以读取文件系统上的任意文件
and using this you can read out arbitrary files on the file system
比如本课程的目标 /flag 文件
for example for the purposes of this class /flag
希望已经讲明白这些漏洞是真实存在的了
so I hope I've convinced you that these vulnerabilities are real
但我相信之后的练习题
but I'm sure that all the practice problems you'll see
会比我现在更能说服你
will do a much better job convincing you of that than I can right now